Hello everyone, and welcome
to the Conf forty-two.
Today we will talk about make agents
observable, tracing decision to cause
and recovery My name is Emerson Braun.
I'm software architect and regional
director at Planate Technologies.
I have more than 15 years in
the software engineering, and
I am creator of AgentsKit.
It's some personal initiative,
don't relate it with Planate
Technologies Let's start.
A agent respond, "Done. The issue
is resolved." Okay, sounds good.
But the reality, the user
still can check it out.
A confidence answer is not evidence
of success, and that will be
the main purpose of this talk.
We need to have observability, and
we need to use some s- techniques
to ensure that we have confidence of
that response And that's is how we
feel when they have a good confidence
of the agent, we cannot prove it
The same answer could have
three different failures.
Okay, it's done, but it's done with that.
With the wrong context,
used a outdate policy.
With a failed action, the refund
never went through, or with an
unverified outcome 'cause the
case, the customer is still waiting
A confidence answer is just a claim.
The agent say the task is complete.
We need to prove it.
Evidence is needed.
What the context used, the instructions
and the data, what was the route selected
and the action was chosen on that.
The outcome verified in
the real world changed.
If we don't have this
tree, it's just a guessing.
It's just some information
that we cannot ensure.
We need to keep the
evidence behind the claim
Observe the execution,
not just the answer.
And the context, what
information the agent used.
In the decision, why using this action?
In the action, what actually happened?
The action was done or not.
And finally, the outcome.
Did it solve the problem?
You sure?
The action was correct,
the policy was outdated.
Think in that scenario.
The user asked for the agent,
"Refund my purchase for 20 days
ago," and the policy used refund
window 30 day, refund was approval.
Okay, no problem.
But the current policy is refund
window is 40 days, not more 30 days.
Can you prove which
version the agent used?
If you're not, you don't have
observability, and definitely you will
have troubles in production Technical
success is different than task success
For example, you have a response, okay?
The integration is replied,
the system receive a response.
It just prove that you have a, a good
connection, but you have a, maybe
a 200 without the, a valid JSON.
You have a a invalid
information with a 200 status.
Then you have to validate as the
same we have in the all APIs we
are using in the daily basis.
We ha- need to validate if the
data is usable, the response
can be parsed and could be used.
And if that JSON
follow the expectation that we have, if
that JSON has all the content we need,
if that JSON has the information that
we will use in some part of our system
And then finally, the task affected.
If the outcome is verified, the
intended status, it was exactly changed.
If we don't have that one, no
matter okay is valid was 200, but
that one don't affect the task
In these days that we are using agents,
I saw something that is really good
for for that, is state machines.
Because with that, we can ensure
the, the steps for the agent could
be go to one step to another, and the
failures, we can retry that one later.
For sure, we need some idempotence key.
But talking about that in each scenario
that you have that state machine, failure
is just a state, is not a conclusion.
Like just dig on that.
For example, a failure could
be in many different scenarios.
We need to preserve the error and
the execution state, and then with
that, we can classify what was failed,
was a timeout or was invalid result.
Then we need to verify the state,
check what actually happened.
With idempotency, we can ensure, okay,
was a creator of a user, was a refound.
What was the action that the agent
tried and with the failure, what
will be the next step in this case?
And then we choose the recovery.
We can retry, we can reroute,
we can compensate that.
For example, if we the agent did
a mistake and that affect the user
budget, definitely compensate will
be interesting in this scenario.
Or we need to escalate that one for
the us- human to do that decision.
And finally, approve the outcome.
The recovery ended with the new evidence.
Add that one in a ledger.
Every single action for the
agents, add that in that ledger.
Later on, you can reconstruct
what was the steps and in every
single what was the outcomes.
If you just update the, the, the current,
you cannot reconstruct step by step.
And don't automate the retries.
Automate the recovery decisions.
Okay, in this scenario, you do this.
In another scenario, you do that.
That you need to automate.
And if uncertain, call the
human In talking about that, the
autonomy need a control boundary.
For example, we have agent that propose
an action, a target, and a scope.
We need to have the policy to
evaluate what was the risk ability
on that, permissions if that agent
has or not, and the evidence.
And then we have, if that one is
a low risk, execute autonomously.
Read, search, classify.
We create some agents
to make your life easy.
If we don't have any autonom-autonomously
part then why we have agents?
In other hand, if that one is
reversible, execute with limits.
That agent could execute that.
We have enough evidence to execute that.
We have that budget that
fit in, in that scenario.
And the, the most important, we have
some idempotency to ensure if we
try that one later on, we will not
duplicate that don't hit the user twice
or don't do the same action twice.
And finally for the high
impact, always approval.
Put the human in the loop.
Okay, the, the agent want to
change something in the database,
but it could affect many users.
Def-- that action need a human to approve
or not that decision, and for sure need
enough information to approve or not.
Not only a agent say, "Okay,
I want to drop a table."
But okay, what is the table?
What is affect?
That table is used in
which environment that one?
Oh, it's just in, in… for the test
environment and no one are using.
Okay then human could approve that
depending of each scenario, for sure.
And I mentioned for observability,
then someone could think, "Okay,
telemetry, observe this," and then
add that one in every single part.
Save every information in, on that.
And but then we can
create another problem.
We need to save the stored
information that we can use later.
If we save every single information and
then we need to s- search for that, we
could have a problem or we could save
a lot of unnecessary information Right.
And we have first the raw execution.
For example, reach,
context, unbounded risk.
On that we have the instructions,
the tool, the, the payloads, the
errors, the credentials, the PII.
Okay, that is the raw execution.
We need to put in the middle
some privacy boundary.
Allowlist, redact, mask the data,
export decisions, and most important,
remove all re-credentials, all
PII, classify the information.
Don't save everything.
Then we have the useful evidence.
Explainable, intentionally limited.
Versions, routes, status, validation,
the outcomes, and reference.
We save that, just the information that
we need later on we need to collect
en-enough information to explain the
system, not enough to recreate the user.
If later on we have this, a lot of
unnecessary information, that will
make it-- our life m-harder, not easy.
If we have this classification
when we ca-grab the information,
definitely we need to reconstruct.
We have just the information necessary
And then we have different kind of agents.
For every single, we need
the different investigation.
For example, for support, the,
the front actually happen.
If we cannot prove it, if we not-- cannot
com-- reconstruct that, we have a problem.
In the automation, did the, for
example, the deployment recover?
For the code, did the validation
pass without the regressions?
For all these, the scenarios is different
agents, but it's the same process.
We need to have the context, decision,
the action and the verified outcome.
If we have that, we have observability.
Another thing that we need
to ensure working with the
agents is some coast guard.
And many of us just think that,
okay, we have the-- that agent
and the model call is we have that
tokens, we have that latency, but
not that is not the, the entire view.
We have to think about them.
We have the tool calls.
We have the database, the search, the
compute, and then we have the retry loops.
Every repeated steps multiply the cost.
Okay we have that model is cheap, but
we call 10 times every single way.
That we have a problem there.
And finally the waiting and the
recovery, the approval, the timeouts,
the fallbacks, the diagnosis.
We need to ensure when we think
about the bill is not just the model
Instrument your next workflow.
You need to have these 10 checks
before you call your agent observable.
Starting the version
instruction and the context.
You have the version of the prompt, you
have the version of the context, and you
have that information saved in some place.
Okay, so you're good.
Record the destructor router decision.
What was the route?
What was the action?
Trace every external boundary.
If your agent touch with some third
part libraries or some third-party
connections with some external
calls with some connections,
trace every external boundary.
Separate request, attempt, and affected.
Later on, when you need to have
this information, will be much
more easy, you can classify that.
Validate outputs semantically.
If you have that, later
on, your life is much easy.
Model recovery as explained states.
As I mentioned, the state machine, if you
can have the every step later on and you
have some idempotency to don't replicate
every time that you try, and you save
that in steps, you can reconstruct later
on, okay, was in that state we need…
We have the retry and what
was the, the next state?
Bind approvals to exact actions.
Okay we have the action
and what was the approval?
Was the, the human approval, and we
have some… That one in the ledger.
Okay, if we have sa- that, we are good.
Redact before the telemetry
export, as I mentioned.
Don't save all the information.
Don't save PII.
Don't save unnecessary
information in the in telemetry.
And measure the verified outcomes.
Okay, that agent have nine, 9% of
security outcomes or m- in this action
we have s- how much amount of retries.
If you have that verified outcomes
later on we you'll have a better
place to investigate what your
bottlenecks, what are parts you
need to improve in your system.
And finally, link metrics
back to the traces.
If you have that you can
easily find the informations.
If you cannot reconstruct the
execution, you cannot operate it.
Okay, now follow the evidence.
Let do some exercise.
We have one instant, two execution
paths, and we… One shared trace model.
Investigate, compare,
review, approve and verify.
That one will be just a scripted
adapter no API no LLM calls on
that one, will be just to exemplify
We have that that example here.
We have this just chat, and the user
want to check the order, and refund that.
Okay.
We send that information, the agent
respond, and choose the action.
And the user, again, confirm the refund.
Okay, that's correct.
We have the human in the
loop, and say that was refund.
We have this some information here what
was request, what was the agent reply.
But we don't have the execution.
We don't have enough information
to, okay, it was correct was not.
The agent say that was was
refund, but we can prove it?
The we have confidence
for that, for sure or not?
And then the same example
with observability.
Same exercise.
We send it, and then we have what the
context loaded what was the context
version, what was the policy version,
of the refund policy version three.
And the policy loaded,
oh is the correct one.
And then the user confirm
the refund confirm created.
Oh, but we received some timeout.
The agent don't have… Is uncertain,
the state because of this observability,
and then need to confirmation was false
that the, the tool returned the timeout.
Okay, let's check the refund status
because maybe the timeout was when
the creation was successful or not.
We need to check it.
Then we check the status, say
the confirm refund was confirmed.
And we can prove it because the tool
refund status have the status confirmed,
and we have the evidence chain.
With that, okay, both was exactly the
same exercise, but one we have, the
steps, the traceability to prove it.
In another, we don't.
Back our presentation.
What proof it worked?
The user could not complete the
checkout or the, the refund.
The recover roll back the
proposal, approved, and executed.
Check the passage, the user flow success.
Recover verified.
The green badge is not the proof.
The verified outcome is.
With the first example maybe was
retry for the agent and it show that.
But without the observability,
without the tracing, we cannot
prove it And that is all.
Don't ask only what agent said.
Ask what happened and what prove it.
Context, decision,
action, outcome, evidence.
If we have that, we are in a good shape.
Thank you again.
That's my LinkedIn, and that
is a link for the live demo.
Thank you, everyone.